♪ [music] ♪
In this exercise, we're going to make this
really sweet JavaScript Drum Kit. I'm not
really exactly sure what it is but it's
really fun to play and when you hit the
corresponding key on your keyboard,
it's going to do two things. First of all,
it's going to play the sound that's
associated with that key and second of
all, it's going to do this short little
animation where it pops the button up to
be a little bit bigger than we want.
And then also, it will apply that yellow
border and that little background there.
It's really, really subtle and I'll show
you how that's working here.
We inspect on this kick one right here.
You see we have this data dash key and
we'll look that in just a second, but when
I press it, you can't even see it adding
because it's going so quickly. But what
that's doing is it's adding a class of
playing to that element which will then
kick in the CSS if I open up today's
exercise and we'll look at stalled at CSS.
You see we have class of playing that's
going to scale it up by 1.1 in our CSS.
It's going to change the border color.
It's going to change the back shadow. Now
because if we look at our regular key
here, you see that we have a transition
that is 0.07 seconds long really,
really quick. And that's going to scale it
up and change the background color behind
it. So that's really the two things that
we have here and if you would like to sort
of go at this on your own, pause the video
here, try to get this up in working.
Otherwise, let's go ahead for the ride and
take a look at what we're working with
here. So we've got a div with class of
keys and inside of that,
we've got a whole bunch of divs with a
class of key. Now, each of these keys here
obviously has like the clap, what sound
it's going to make as well as the key that
you should hit on your keyboard. But the
important thing here is that every key on
your keyboard when you press the up or the
down, when you key up or key down event,
there is going to be something called the
key code that is associated with that key.
Now, I've got a little website here I
whipped up a couple of years ago because I
always find myself searching for it and
it's called keycode.info and when you
press a key on your keyboard like escape
or space or A, it's going to have number
associated with that specific key on your
keyboard and this is the most consistent
way that I found across browser, cross
languages. It's not absolutely perfect
but it gets you most of the way for most
of your standard keys. When you click
or when you hit 65 like when you key up
and we're going to check if that was the A
key then we're going to play the
corresponding audio element that also has
the data-key. Now, what is this data dash
key? If you've never used a data
attributes before, this is not a standard.
You won't find this Googling anything,
anywhere you want. And essentially, data
attributes were brought about in HTML when
people were just making up their own
attributes. We have things like source and
class, and those are standards. And then
people just started making up their own
and the people who made HTML were like,
"whoa, whoa, whoa, chill out,
you can't just start adding shit like for
whatever you want." So we came up with
this idea of data attributes where if you
want to make up something like a key,
you have to put it behind a data-something
So what I'm doing here is I'm
using data attributes to hook up this, the
data key 65 along with the data key audio.
So that when someone hits the key on their
keyboard, we're going to find the audio
element and play it and we're going to
find the key div and we're going to add a
class of playing so it will animate itself
on in. So let's get started,
go over to our script tag here and the
first thing we need to do is just be
focused on listening for a key up event.
Now, the way that we do that is you first
get whatever element that you're
listening for and in our case,
I'm going to listen on the window.
Sometimes, you might want to listen on the
input or a div or a text area or something
like that. And we're going to add an event
listener. The event that we're
listening here is called key down.
And then next, we have a function which
will give us the event and inside of that,
we have nothing. And then I'm going to get
rid of the rest of this stuff here.
So we're going to listen for the key down
event and when that happens,
we're going to run this function which
will give us the event and I'm just going
to console log that event. Open up my
console, now whenever I press one of these
keys on the keyboard, you'll see that we
get this keyboard event, that's what E is.
The event is just the object full of data
describing what happened and it'll tell us
all kinds of info like what key was
actually hit. But the thing we're
concerned with here the key code, which is
the number that is associated with that
key, and that's essentially what all this
website is. When someone hits the key up,
we're just going to display the
corresponding number that you have.
So we go down here, we can log
e.keyCode and see what we've got.
Good, now we've got all these different...
If you hit spacebar, you can get 32.
If you hit escape, you're going to get 27.
Now what we need to do is say,
"is there an audio element on the page
that has a data dash key of 65?" And we're
going to use document.querySelector
because we're only looking for one.
If I was looking for many, I would say
query selector all but in our case it's
just query selector. And we're going to
listen for an audio, we're going to try to
select an audio element but we want to
select it where it has a data - key,
like there's no class on here. And
sometimes I see people say like,
"class=key-65" and they'll split it and
select something with a class of key 65.
That's a bit messy to me. I'd rather just
use its own data attribute here.
So we can use and attribute selector if
you've ever used this in CSS,
works the same in JavaScript. Attribute
selector say something like this,
"data-key=" and normally would say 65,
right? But that is going to be a variable
that lives inside of this event. So what
I'm going to do is I'm going to switch
these to back text and we're going to use
ES6 template strings which is dollar sign
curly brackets say "e.keyCode." Now, we
can console log audio and see if we have
selected an actual audio element. So I'm
going to refresh, I'm going to hit my A
button. No, we got an error,
audio(data-key=65) is not a valid
selector. What did we do here? I think we
need to pop a set of quotes around this
actual key here. Let's see if that works
for us. Hit A. There we go.
So it looks like you do need quotes around
your actual number here. Now when I hit
the key, and hit S, I'm going to
hit D. You see that we are getting the
corresponding audio element for that
specific key. Now sometimes we're going to
hit, I'm going ahead and hit Q. We get
null. Why do we get null?
That's because there is no audio element
associated with 81. So right away,
right there we can do is we can say if
there is no audio, if bang audio,
then we are just going to return. And that
would just stop the function from running
altogether. Okay, good, and that would
just stop it. Now what we can do since we
have this audio element, we can
play it. Let's try that. S, D, F.
Now it kind of works but here, hit F
over and over again, F, F, F, F.
I'm hitting it multiple times, but it
really only plays once every so often.
And that's because the open hat F, it
plays and it takes like maybe two or three
seconds to actually get to the end. And if
you call .play on an audio element
that is already playing, it won't play it
again because it's like,
"oh, why would I do that? I'm clearly
already playing with that." So what we
want to do before we do that is sort of
rewind it to the start of the element so
that if you hit it in succession over and
over again and over again,
it will just rewind it to the start. So
let's say "audio.currenTime=0." Now this
is going to rewind to the start. And now
if I just hammer on F,
you see we get it over and over again,
AAAA, SSS, DDD, FFF.
Good, playing over and over again. I'm
going to try some of the other keys on the
keyboard, nothing happens because we're
doing this check if there's no audio
element. Now, what we also need to do is
select the corresponding key that is with
it because we want to add that little
animation that we have here.
So let's say "const key=" and I going to
take this entire thing and switch it out
with a dot key. So instead of selecting an
audio element with the data dash key,
we could select a div or in our case,
something with the class of key but also
the data dash key. Now, let's go to the
bottom here and console log the actual key
element. Good, look these are the
corresponding key elements that we have,
and how do we get them to do that
cool little animation? Well,
again, if we go back to our style.CSS
we've got here, you see that I've already
styled the CSS and most of this does not
matter except the one line that we have
here that is transition all 0.07 seconds.
And when you add a class of playing to
that, we're going to scale it up, we're
going to change the border color and we're
going to change the box shadow color. So,
what we can do is we'll say,
"key.classList.add" and then we'll say
"playing." If you've never used this,
if you're just used to using jQuery,
that's the same thing as saying like
"key.addClass(playing)." Except we're not
using jQuery here, we're just using
Vanilla JavaScript, so that's the way
that you do it in Vanilla JavaScript.
You call .classList and then add.
Similarly, we also have .remove and we
have .toggle which will allow you to add
and remove the different classes that
you want. So let's see how that works
S, D, F. You see how it's adding them?
If you want to see how it works a little
bit slower, what you can do is go into
your CSS and change this, maybe let's make
the scale two and let's make the
transition 1.07 seconds. Now when I hit D,
you see over a second, F, G.
That's what's happening but because
we did it in such a short time span,
0.07 seconds, it just does it really,
really quickly and also,
we don't want to scale it up exactly that
much. Now, that works but why isn't it
going away? That's because we are adding
the class but we have not yet removed the
class. You might think, "oh, that's no
problem, we'll do like a set timeout here,
we'll run a function here and after 0.07
seconds." Well, that's okay but what tends
to happen if you have a timeout here as
well as you have a timeout in your CSS
JavaScript which is right here, they start
to get out of sync because maybe like a
designer comes around like, "its not quite
right, let's change that to like 0.9,
that feels a little bit better to me." And
then you have to go into the JavaScript to
make that that lines up as well. So rather
than like just setting a timer to do it,
what we can do is use a transition end
event that will fire when the thing has
stopped animating itself on in. Now, what
is the transition end event?
Well, let's take it back a second, what is
a click event? The click event is when you
click something and it will fire off the
event and say, "somebody clicked me." We
also have events in JavaScript that will
say, "I didn't get clicked but I was
transitioned, I transition myself from
scale 1 border black to scale 1.1 border
yellow." That's what we're going from here
which is the border black to here which
the border is that specific yellow. So
what we can do is we can listen on each
key for when the transition end event
happens. So let's do that.
First, let's go down here and we'll say
"const key=" now I need to select every
single key on the page because we want to
listen for it on each one.
So let's say "document.querySelector" and
we want query selector all, and we'll say
dot key. Now let's just see if I were to
run that in my console here,
let's see what that gives us. That gives
us an array of every single element that
is matched. Okay, good, then what we
want to do is we want to listen for
an event called transition end on each
one. So it's like "keys.forEach" and we're
going to get each key. If you're
wondering why do we have to this,
like why can't we just do
"keys.addEventListener" and listen for
transition end? And that's because if
you're used jQuery or anything like that,
the problem is when you have an array
of elements, you cannot listen on all of
them. You must explicitly loop over every
singly element and attach an event
listener. So, the way that I like to that
seems to be the simplest way for me is
you can say key. We use a little arrow
function here, if you've followed along in
my ES6 series, it's "key.addEventListener"
and then the listener that we're listening
for is transition end, and when that ends,
we are going to run a function called
"remove transition." Now we have to make
that. Now, let's just take a quick look
at here. So each key gets an event
listener added to it which is transition
end. And then when a transition is ending,
we will remove it. Now we need to actually
make that function here. So let's say
"function removeTransition" and that let's
give us the event. Inside of that, we'll
just console log the event just to see
what we're working with here. So, I'm
going to press A. Whoa, what happened
here? Okay, so we have one, two, three,
four, five, six transition end events for
that one little fade in where it got a
little bit bigger. And that's because a
whole bunch of things transitioned here.
The border right color transition,
all of the borders have transitioned. The
box shadow which is that little yellow
glow has transitioned. And then also,
the transform has finished.
Now, we don't really care about all of
these. We really just want to it when one
thing is over, generally the longest one.
So, let's pick the transform.
So, let's say "if E." and what was the
event we were looking for here
"event.propertyName." If it doesn't equal
transition then we will return.
And now we'll say "skip it if it's not a
transform." Transform,
not transition, I always mess them up.
Thank you for yelling at me through the
computer screen. Now, what's up next?
Let's just console log e.propertyName.
Let's see what we're working with here. So
we got this function that will run when a
transition has ended. You see what's
happening? It's console logging the word
transform because that is the property
that is being ended. Now,
that does it really quickly, but if I were
again to change this transform to 2.07
seconds and press A, one, two there we go.
It took seconds and then that's when it
ended. And coincidentally, why
coincidentally? That's why we want to do
it. When that happens, when it's done
moving itself in, we just want to reverse
everything that we know about that. So we
can head to our remove transition function
here and first of all, we'll save this.
Now what is this going to be equal to?
Well, if you are having a hard time
understanding what this is equal to
a really cheap and dirty way to understand
what this is equal to, well first you just
console log and see what it is.
That's a nice a way to find it out.
So, let me press A and then after two
seconds, I still have it on two seconds.
This is equal to the key, and why is that?
Because this is always equal to the
whatever got called against it. So add
event listener got called,
what got called against it, key.
So this is equal to the actual key.
So this, .classlist.remove we'll remove
the class of playing. Give that a save.
Now it's two seconds so I'm going
to hit it. Two seconds later,
transition end is going to fire which is
going to remove the transition of playing
and it should fade itself out. So, I'm
going to hit D, it's in and it's done
and it'll take the class off. If we
inspect that, watch it right here.
See, it's got a class of playing and then
two seconds later, it will remove it.
Now, if we go to our CSS and change
that back to 0.07 seconds,
it's just nice and quick, nice and quick,
nice and quick for all of those,
it went immediately. And the same thing
happens there if you were to add a class
of playing in div tools. It will still
remove it because the JavaScript is
listening on that element for when you
remove it. One last thing I want to do is
we go into our HTML. I'm never a big fan
of attaching these functions right to the
key down here, so what I want to do is put
these in its own function and it will call
that play sound. Let's say "function
playSound" and put all these logic inside
here and that is going to take in the
event which then bring down my event
listener down to the bottom here and we're
going to say when someone keys down
we're going to play the sound, that should
keep it for us. Still works fine
and that we've got them nice and separate
so that if I ever wanted to play the sound
based off on something else, I totally
could. So that is a basic JavaScript
Drum Kit. Again, the things we learned
about was key events as well as playing
audio as well listening for the transition
end event. Similarly, if you're also
dealing with animations, you can listen
for the animation end event, which works
exactly the same way. Thank you so much
and I'll see you in the next one.
♪ [music] ♪