♪ [music] ♪
Today what we'll be building is this
sweet HTML5 canvas where,
as I click down, drag my finger and let
go, it's going to draw something on the
actual canvas here. Now, this may seem a
little bit silly, but we're actually going
to learn a lot about how the fundamentals
of Canvas actually work,
as well as a couple other
neat tricks along the way.
So let's head on over to our
JavaScript file here, and really,
all we have is this Canvas element that we
need to draw on. So first thing that we
want to do is grab that canvas, and the
second thing that we need is something
called a context. Canvas on the
web is sort of like Microsoft Paint,
where you just get a block of actual
pixels and you need to then draw on that.
Now, you don't draw directly on the canvas
element in HTML, but you draw on something
called the context. And the context can
either be 2D, which is what we'll be
working with, although you can also use it
with 3D for the stuff like video games and
3D rendering. So we're going to grab
the context, const ctx = canvas.
Getcontext. Ask it for the 2D context.
Next thing we need to do is size up our
canvas to be the exact width of the
window. By default, your canvas is going
to be 800px by 800px, as I've done it
here. However, we want to resize it before
we do any of our drawings. So say
canvas.width = window.innerWidth and we'll
also do that with height. Then, when I
refresh this page, it should be as big as
the actual window is. If I Inspect Element
on my canvas element you shouldn't see
anything, but if you hover over it, you'll
see mine is about 1700px by 1100px.
Then we need to do a couple of the base
settings with the strokeStyle,
the lineCap and the lineJoin, and I'll
explain these in just a second.
#BADA55. And we need lineJoin is going to
be round, and the lineCap is also going to
be round. And when you draw on something,
what is going to happen is there needs to
be a color, first of all, and we're going
to start with #BADA55,
and then also the end of the line, should
it be squared off? And when a line meets
another line, should it be squared off or
should it be rounded around the corner?
So we've done rounded. You can go up on
MDN and look at all the different options
for lineJoin and lineCap,
and play around with them.
Next, we need a couple of dummy variables,
so we're going to say let isDrawing =
false, and what this is going to do is
when I click down on this element...
I'm clicking down, I just did it, and I
move my mouse and then I let go,
and then I move my mouse again. Nothing
happens when I'm moving my mouse down,
it only draws when my cursor is actually
down. So what we're going to do is we're
creating sort of like a flag right here,
where we set it to false,
and then when you click down we set it to
true, and when you click up,
you let go of the button, we're going to
set it to false. And that's sort of just
going to be our flag to tell us should we
actually draw to this canvas,
or is someone moving their mouse
without doing anything?
Then we need a couple of variables,
let lastX = 0 and lastY = 0.
And lastX and lastY are going to help us
out, because when we draw to a canvas,
let's say I have my mouse right here and I
want to move it to right here.
Let's imagine that was just one straight
line. What needs to happen for you to draw
a line is you need a starting X and Y and
an ending X and Y. You can't just tell it
"Draw a line at coordinates (100,100),"
because a line needs a start and a stop,
not just a start. So what we've done is
we've created a lastX and a lastY variable
that's going to be "Where do you start the
line from?" And then when we finish
drawing, that's going to be "Where do you
end?" Next up, we need a function called
draw, and that's going to take in an
event. That draw function is going to be
called whenever I move my mouse on top of
the canvas. Let's just console.log that
event, and we'll listen for our
mousemove event on the canvas.
So now when I move my mouse on the canvas,
it's going to console.log draw,
and when I move around our mouse now,
you're going to see that these events,
MouseEvents, are being logged every time
I move the mouse. And on those
MouseEvents, we're going to see offsetX,
offsetY, movementX, movementY,
X and Y. All this information about what
happened, where was the mouse when this
thing was fired. But, again, we don't want
this draw, this console log to run all the
time, we want to only do it when the
person has clicked down. So what we can do
here is, we'll say if they are not drawing
then return. And this will stop the
function from running when they are not
moused down. And then how do we change
that isDrawing? Well, we'll have another
event listener here, so mousedown.
And when the mouse is down, we're just
going to run a quick arrow function inline
here that says isDrawing = true, and when
the mouse is up isDrawing = false,
and then finally one, we want to listen
for mouseout isDrawing is also going to be
false. Because what can happen is you can
click down, let your mouse leave the
actual window here and let go and come
back, and it's still going to think that
the mouse is down because you never
triggered a mouseup on that event.
So when you mouse out it's going to
automatically say, "Oh, you're no longer
drawing." So with these variables being
set here, we should only console.log the
event when my mouse is down. So refresh,
here we go, I'm moving my mouse around,
nothing is happening. I'm going to click
and keep moving my mouse,
look at all these numbers are moving and
I'm going to let go and move my mouse
around, nothing happening. Good. So that
means this function, everything below this
one line, is only going to run when the
user's mouse is actually down.
So that's our sort of click-and-drag
functionality down pat, now let's work on
actually doing the drawing.
So first thing we want to do here
is start a path, so we say ctx,
and remember, ctx is where we do all of
our drawings for our canvas.
So beginPath() then we need to start with
an X and a Y, move it to an X and Y,
and that will complete our drawing of X.
So we say ctx.moveTo (lastX,
lastY), and then we are going
to lineTo (e.offsetX, e.offsetY).
And again, those e.offsetX and offsetY,
those values are coming from the actual
event that happened here. And
then finally we call ctx.stroke().
So all of these lines right here, they've
just been starting up our line,
but we're not going to actually see
anything on the page until we call stroke.
Now, that's not going to get us there, but
let's see where we are so far.
Whoa! What is going on here? Maybe you
can understand what's going on here.
It's actually kind of cool. We're drawing
all of these lines, but what's happening
is we're always starting from...and we'll
put a comment, "Start from," and "Go to."
We're going to always start from 0, and go
to wherever the user's mouse is actually
moving, right? So what we want to do is
when we're done, this draw function,
we want to update the lastX and the lastY
variables to be wherever they were.
So we could say lastX = e.offsetX and
lastY = e.offsetY. Let's see if that does
it for us. Ah, working so far. Drag...oh,
no. A couple of things happening here.
First of all, let me just show you a quick
ES6 trick. We could set both of these
variables in one line where we say
[lastX, lastY] = [e.offsetX, e.offsetY].
That just allows us to do it in one single
line. That's called "destructuring an
array," but we still have this problem. We
got a couple of problems here.
First of all, when I click down my first
drawing is still always going to start at
(0,0), and that doesn't really make much
sense. And then the other thing is,
like, when I continue to draw, it just
starts off from where I was.
So I'm only able to draw one continuous
line and nowhere in between.
What we can do is go back to this
mousedown, here, this function,
and maybe I'll move this to the top here,
just have it out. And rather than doing
this just one quick inline function, I'm
going to make that into a block so I can
do multiple things. So isDrawing = true,
but we also have to update our lastX and
our lastY, the same as we've done here and
pass the event. So what we're going to do
is as soon as the person clicks their
mouse down to start it, before we do a
mousemove, because mousedown
will happen before we move our mouse,
then we're going to update the lastX and
lastY, and that's going to put us where we
want to go rather than starting
at (0,0). So give that a save.
Now, I'm going to start here. Click.
Ah, looks like it's actually working.
Can I start another one? Good. Draw
another line. Draw another line.
Draw another line. Good. I'm really happy
with that. Now, couple of other things.
These lines are really, really small so we
could go up to our context here and say
ctx.lineWidth = 100, and that will give us
a much... You see how the end of the caps
are round? If I were to take this lineJoin
and lineCap off, we just get that,
woo! This kind of funkiness going on here,
and as well as the lineCap it's going to
give us this nice, smooth round one. So
that's the very basics of drawing on a
canvas, but let's have a little bit of fun
and do something like this.
Let's first do the color. If you haven't
heard of HSL, I need to stop for just a
second and explain it. Head to
the website mothereffinghsl.com,
and what HSL is, it's essentially the
rainbow, but you can programmatically
select pieces of the rainbow. So the hue
part of HSL is from red all the way over
to red on the rainbow, the S which is the
saturation, which is sort of like,
how bright it is. And L is going to be the
lightness and that's what you can change
right here. Lightness all the way is
white, the absence of lightness is going
to be black. So somewhere in the middle is
probably what you're looking for,
maybe a little bit higher and that's going
to allow us to programmatically pick the
different pieces of this. Now, that's
really cool because what we can do is if 0
is red, and 360 is the other spectrum,
that means for every 360 draws that we do,
we can just pick and increment
a color and then flip it back.
So what we're going to do is go
back up to our initial variables,
and we're going to say let hue = 0
and as we draw, before we begin the path,
we'll say ctx.strokeStyle, and remember
we started with #BADA55,
but now we're going to be setting it to be
'hsl ()', and the hue is going to be the
variable hue, and then we're going to give
it 100% saturation and 50% lightness.
So let's start, let's see where we get
so far. Yeah, so it's starting at 0,
which is red . Good, but we could also,
once we've done that strokeStyle,
or maybe at the end of it here, we say
hue++, and that will just increment it so
the second time we draw it will be 1.
Third time will be 2. Woo!
Okay, looking good. Looking good. And
eventually, we're just going to get all
the way around and the kind of the cool
part about HSL is if you go over 360,
it's just going to...like if we pop it
into here and see what hue is that,
hue is 906 but it'll just kind of, like,
keep going around and around and around.
What we could also do is say if(hue >=
360) then hue = 0 and then just sort of,
like, reset it at that point
and that will work just as well.
And then the other thing that we can do is
we can also change the lineWidth of what
we've done right here, ctx.lineWidth.
We can use that variable as well.
So, strokeStyle...ctx.lineWidth is going
to be equal to hue. Let's see what we got
there. So it starts...ooh, it goes
all the way up, all the way up,
all the way up, and then at a certain
point, it just starts over again.
And that's kind of cool, but what I've
done here is once you hit that maximum
draw it will just sort of fade itself
back. So what we can do is create another
variable here called let direction = true.
That means it's going to be building up,
so we have let direction = true,
now we have this lineWidth = hue.
We don't want this, delete that line and
head down to the bottom below where we do
our hue stuff, and we are going to, for
every loop, we are going to increment the
line width. So ctx.lineWidth++. What that
will do is it will increment the lineWidth
once for every single time I have, so
growing bigger, bigger, bigger and it just
keeps getting bigger and bigger and bigger
infinitely, and that's really not what we
want. So what you can say is we'll say if
(ctx.lineWidth >= 100 | | ctx.lineWidth <=
1) then we want to flip the direction.
Then we say down here
if(direction = true)
then the lineWidth goes up, otherwise
the lineWidth goes down.
Now, that might have broken your brain
for a second, so let's take a second
to see what's going on here, if(ctx.
lineWidth) is greater than 100,
so essentially what we're doing right here
is we're incrementing it from 0 all the
way to 100, but then once we hit 100,
we're going to go from 100 to 99 to 98,
all the way down. So we're saying, if it's
greater than 100, then flip the direction,
or if it's less than 1, also flip the
direction. And then, depending on what
that direction is, we either increment the
line width, or if the direction is going
in the other way, we decrement the line
width by 1. So let's see what's going on
here. Draw, draw, draw, and
it's going smaller, bigger, bigger,
bigger. Smaller, smaller, smaller. Bigger,
bigger, bigger. And you can play with
these values as well, you could do it
something like 500 where it gets super big
and then it will slowly bring itself
down once we get to 500.
There we go, it's bringing itself down to
be much smaller. You can play with it
exactly. One other thing we can do is play
with something called Global Composite
Operator, and if you've worked with
Photoshop blend modes, you can use blend
modes inside of context. So say ctx.
globalCompositeOperation = 'multiply'.
This is kind of cool where when you draw
on it... Let me refresh this here.
They will sort of blend each other as you
draw over top of each other.
Eventually, everything is just going to be
black, but you can play with the different
blend modes that we have here, the
subtract and lighten and all that good
stuff. So just go and look up Global
Composite Operator on Google and take a
look at the different types that we have
here. They've got a nice source-over,
source-in, source-out, source-atop,
destination-over. Just play with all of
them and you can kind of get an idea
for how are they actually working.
So that is today's exercise. We had fun
with Canvas. We understood couple things
about events and when events happen.
We understand this flag thing,
where you set it to isDrawing = true and
isDrawing = false, that's sort of a common
thing that we do a lot in JavaScript where
you have a flag where you want to test if
it's true or not and then when you move
the mouse, we use the event information to
draw onto our canvas context.
Hopefully, you enjoyed that.
I'll see you in the next one.
♪ [music] ♪