♪ [music] ♪
Hi, everybody. Wes Bos here. We are
going to make a photobooth with JavaScript
today. Now, first of all, if you see like
I'm talking, and then later on the audio
doesn't add up, that's because I'm
recording my screen on a 4K monitor and
piping video through, and it's just too
much. So when I stop recording my screen,
this is live, don't worry if you wonder if
the sound is off or not.
So what are we going to be building today?
First of all, we've got our video being
piped in from our webcam, and then we've
got our video being piped into a canvas
element. Then, once it's in a canvas
element, we can start to do all kinds of
cool things with it. Like we can take our
photo, and then you can go ahead and
download them. They'll download to your
computer, and you can see them as real
photos, handsome.png. Then, in the
scripts, once we have it, we can start to
add effects, like different filters where
things should be red.
Or what we can do is make this really cool
RGB split, where you can see my face.
Don't look at the top right-hand corner, I
look crazy. But the RGB values are just a
little bit off. You can play with the
alpha. So it's just a bit of like a,
woo, ghosting effect that goes on here.
Then, finally, the green screen.
If you've never known how the green screen
works, essentially you pick a color that's
in the background, and then you find any
color that's within the range of that
specific color, usually green, and then
you pull it out. Whatever is behind it,
like a video or a beach, or something like
that, it's going to show.
So we have these slider values here, which
we can use to discover what the threshold
is, and in my case I'm pulling out just a
whole bunch of stuff,
but you can do some fun stuff. Whatever
would be behind that would then show on
through. So this is going to be a bit of a
big one, but it's going to be fun.
So let's get rolling. I'll open up my
index.html and switch this
scripts-FINISHED to just scripts.js, and
it'll go into our scripts.js.
Before we get started today, there is one
thing that we do need to get up and
running, and that is a server. So far, in
this course we've just been working off of
the file. We right-click and that sucker
in the browser. However,
because of security restrictions with
getting a user's webcam,
it must be tied to what's called a "secure
origin". A secure origin is a website that
is HTTPS, or in our case localhost is also
a secure origin. Even if it's not,
has a little icon lock there, it's still
considered a secure origin,
which is localhost. So what I need you to
do, if you take a look at this,
we have this index.html, that needs to be
fed through some sort of server.
So if you've already got Python server or
maybe Map if you've done WordPress,
or any sort of local server running, you
can totally use that.
Just make sure that you feed this
index.html through your localhost server.
Now, if you don't have any sort of server
locally, what I've done is I've included a
package.JSON file. If we open that up,
you'll see that I have one dependency,
which is this thing called "browser-sync".
It's really, really nice,
because it allows you to open up your
website and start a little server,
and it also gives you live reloading and a
whole bunch of other stuff.
So what I want you to do is type "npm
install". If you don't have NPM,
if it tells you that's not something, you
go to nodejs.org and download Node.js.
So I'm going to type "npm install", and
when that has finished what you can type
is "npm start". What that is going to do,
it's going to run this script that I have
here and this is just a really long
browser-sync start file. This just starts
a little server for you. So "npm start",
and that is going to kick open a little
server. It's going to tell you that your
local server is 3001,
and then it will also give you an external
server in case you want to check it on
your Wi-Fi, maybe check it on your Android
phone, or something like that.
So I've got that up and running. Now,
let's go to our scripts.js,
and I'm going to load in a couple
selectors that we're working with here,
just because you're probably sick of
seeing me type selectors for now.
Let's review real quick. We've got this
video here, which is a class of "player".
If we look at our HTML, you'll see that we
have a canvas, we have a video,
and we have a strip. Now, the video from
our webcam is going to come in hot off the
webcam, and we're going to pipe that into
this video element. Then,
every, I don't know, 16 milliseconds or
so, we're going to take a snapshot of that
video and dump it into this canvas. Once
it's in the canvas, we're going to
manipulate the pixels, change the color,
apply filters. We're going to have a lot
of fun with that. But just know that the
video is going to come off the webcam on
the video element, and we're going to dump
it into the canvas every so often.
Then, finally the strip, that's where
we're going to put all of our images.
So what that canvas video context, this is
where the work happens.
If you've never used canvas before, go
back to our canvas tutorial that we've
done earlier. We've got our strip, and
then we have this audio,
which is a little [verbal sounds 00:05:17]
sound that's going to play every single
time that we play a video here. Good. The
first thing we want to do is get the video
being piped into that video element. So
we're going to say "function getVideo".
The way that you get
someone's video, it's actually
"navigator.mediaDevices.getUserMedia".
If you've done this before,
you might have seen it as
"navigator.getUserMedia". It's now changed
to "navigator.mediaDevices" in some of the
newer browsers, which is "getUserMedia".
From that we pass it to the video, which
we want to be "true" and the audio,
which is going to be "false". Now that
thing this going to return a promise.
You know that with a promise, we call
".then" on it. It's going to give us
something called a "localMediaStream".
From there, we'll run a function.
Let's just console.log that
"localMediaStream", see what we've got
here. So when you load it, you probably
get a little pop-up here saying "localhost
would like to access your camera". Go
ahead and click Yes to that,
and of course we need to run this getVideo
function on page load.
You'll notice it's refreshing
automatically for you, which is a really
nice feature. So here's what we've got
here. We've got this media stream,
and then we've just got some ID, "active:
true", and there's some stuff on the
prototype that we're working with here.
But really not much for us to deal with.
So what we need to do is to take our
video, and we need to set the source to be
that "localMediaStream". Now, that's not
going to work automatically,
because this is an object. In order for
our video to work, it actually needs to be
converted into some sort of URL. This is a
little bit weird, because you might be
used to having a video like a .mp4. But
this is how you set it to be a live video
feed. So we're going to wrap this
"localMediaStream" in window.url caps
".createObjectURL". That's going to
convert that media stream into something
that this video player can understand.
Finally, underneath that we'll call
"video.play", which is going to play it.
If I try it with that,
you might see like one frame. Yeah, see?
One frame. If you mouse over it,
it will sometimes open. Why is that?
That's because we set the video to be this
media stream. But it's not going to update
unless we actually go ahead and play it.
So I'm going to call "video.play". Now,
when you load the page,
you should see yourself in the actual
video element in the top right-hand corner
that I've done here. If you inspect it,
you'll see that the video source is a
blob. That just means that it's the raw
data being piped in off this webcam right
here. The last thing that we need to do is
we need to do a catch here,
just in case someone doesn't allow you to
access their webcam.
We need to handle that error. So we'll say
"error", and when that happens we're just
going to console.error. Oh, no, and then
give yourself the error.
You can obviously tell the user, "Hey, you
denied the webcam. Maybe you should not do
that, because we need to get access to
your webcam." Good. So we are up and
running with getting the video being piped
in. The next thing that we need to do is
to take a frame from this video, and to
paint it onto the actual canvas on the
screen. So that's what we'll do here, is
we'll make a function and we will call
that "paintToCanvas". We have a couple
things first. What we need is the width
and the height of the actual video. So
we'll say "const width = video.videowidth"
and "const height = video.videoheight".
Now, what we need to do is the video is
going to have a width and height
associated with it, and if we were to call
that "paintToCanvas" you'll see that it's
640 by 480. That's the size of the video
that's coming in off my webcam. Now, we
need to make sure that the canvas is the
exact same size before we paint to it.
That's really important because if the
canvas is not the same size as the video
or if your video webcam has a different
width and height to it, then we need to
change that. So we'll say "canvas.width =
width" and "canvas.height = height". Good.
Now, if you refresh and you inspect this
canvas here, you'll see that right now
it's 943 pixels. But if I were to call
that "paintToCanvas", it will then be
changed. It still shows me it,
because I'm stretching it with CSS. But
the width and the height have been
explicitly set on the actual canvas. Now,
what we want to do is to every,
I don't know, 16 or so milliseconds, we
are going to take an image from the webcam
and put it into the canvas. So we are
going to "setinterval", and that is going
to run a function every... Let's start
with 16 milliseconds. You really have to
play with how often is it going to paint
to the canvas. A lower-performance
machine, sometimes you have to go up. You
can also play with
"requestAnimationFrame". But I have had no
success with that, so I'm sticking with an
interval here. We're going to take the
canvas context, we're going to call
"dramImage", and you simply just pass it
your video element. So the way that
"dramImage" works is that you pass it an
image, or a video element,
and it will paint it right to it. We're
going to start at 00, which is I guess
you're on the other side here. Start at
the top left-hand corner of the canvas,
and then paint the width and the height.
That's exactly why we stuck them in their
own variables right here. So if we rerun
that "paintToCanvas" now...
Oh, we got an error, "setInterval". It's
capital I. It probably drives you nuts
watching me code like that. There we go.
Woo. What's going on here?
Every 16 milliseconds what's happening is
this is our canvas element right here,
and then up here we've got our video
element that we're working with.
So we are taking a frame from it. One
thing I like to do is just return that
interval here, because if you ever need to
stop this from painting,
you can have access to that interval and
you can call "clearInterval" on it.
Good. Now, what we want to do is let's
work on the takePhoto function,
so "function takePhoto". Let's work on the
audio portion of it right now.
So I'll say "snap.currentTime = 0" and we
will say "snap.play".
So Console, Refresh. We want to go into
our console and run "paintToCanvas".
Got it going. Then, we're going to run
"takePhoto", which should play.
There we go. You might not hear it,
because it's not recording on my
computer's audio. But that should say
[verbal noise 00:12:38].
Just imagine it going off right now. Good.
So that is playing the photo.
But before we go any further, it's kind of
a pain to have to manually run this
"paintToCanvas". So what we're going to do
is we're going to go down to the bottom
here. We're going to listen for an event
on the video element called "canplay".
So we're going to say
"video.addEventListener('canplay')".
That's an event that the video will emit.
When that happens, we are going to run the
function "paintToCanvas". So what will
that do? Once this video is played,
it's going to emit... Because we've got to
get the webcam sorted out first.
Right? Once the video is playing, it's
going to emit an event called "canplay",
which in turn canvas is going to say, "Oh,
now we should start to paint to canvas."
So that's going to now happen on our page
load. Good. I'm happy with that.
Now, how do we take a photo of this actual
canvas here. So it's part of our
"takePhoto". We've already played the
sound, which is not really anything to do
with it. What we now need to do is take
the data out of the canvas.
We can do this, "const data =
canvas.toDataURL". Then, you pass it,
"image/jpeg" or "jpng", or whatever you're
looking for. But it probably makes sense
to do a PJEG with an E there, because
that's a picture of me. It's not really a
PNG. Then, I'm just going to console.log
the actual data and see what we're working
with here. So I'm going to go to my
console, and see what we're working with
here. I'm going to take a photo. Okay, and
this is what happens.
Whoa. What the heck is this? So what this
is, this is something called "Base64".
This is like a text-based representation
of the picture of me.
So this like "8vpb4fb", that means
"stunning smile". This "rvs0",
that means "sweet baby blues". These are
just like little attributes about the
photo in text-based form. So what we can
do with that is we can create a link and
an image to actually put it into our
strip. Let's create a link here.
So we'll say "const link =
document.createElement". You need to
create a proper link here. You can't just
use back text. Then,
we will be creating an anchor link. That
"link.href" is going to equal the data.
That's what we have there. Then, we are
also going to say "link.setAttribute".
The attribute we are going to set is
called "download", and we're going to set
that to "handsome". I'll show you why in
just a second. Then, we'll just say
"link.textContent = _'Download Image'_".
Then, finally, we are going to take our
strip, which is where we're going to dump
our links. We are going to insert before
and we're going to insert the link node.
It's going to happen right before the
strip.firstChild. That's sort of like if
you've jQueried ".prepend",
this is how you do that in vanilla
JavaScript. So what we did is we created a
link. We set the href... Apparently "href"
is not a word, but let's make it a thing.
".setAttribute", ".textContent", we've
created the link, and we've put it in.
So let's see what we've got here. It's
running. I'm going to run the function
"takePhoto". Good. Now, we have a link
here that is "download photo".
I'm going to open it up in a new tab,
first of all. Whoa. Look what we've got
here. So this, the URL, is just a data
image here. But it's smart enough to know
that that is the actual image. It's not
anywhere on our computer.
It's just stored in this really long text
string. But what I also did is we made
this download attribute of "handsome", and
when you click that it's going to
actually, there we go, download it to your
computer, where it will then be put on
your user's hard drive. You can then open
it up in your Finder,
whatever it is you're using. There we go,
"handsome.jpeg". I've got it up and
running. Cool. So we've got our download
"download image". We've got it.
Now, let's actually put the image visible
inside of there as well.
So rather than link that text content,
delete that. We'll say "link.innerHTM" is
equal to an image tag". The source is
going to be equal to the data.
So both the href and the source is going
to be equal to the data.
[inaudible 00:17:32] "Handsome Man",
adjust accordingly if you're not
handsome. When we run "takePhoto", there
we go, you should now see your actual
photo. Every time you run that function,
it's going to take a photo of yourself,
and you can download any of the ones that
you like. Cool. Let's hook it up to the
actual button. So if we go to our
index.html and we have this photo,
it's already hooked up on click, or you
could select it. I've just did sort of
like a bit of a cheap way to do it without
selecting it, and that button should now
work regardless of whatever it is that
you're doing. Good. So we've got our
"getVideo". We've got our "paintToCanvas".
We've got our "takePhoto".
Really, the last thing that we want to do
is do some filters on them.
So the way that a filter works is that you
get the pixels out of the canvas,
and then you mess with them, changing the
RGB values, and put them back in.
So let's go back up to our
"paintToCanvas". Let's go into our
interval, and we'll just do something like
this and say, "const pixels =
ctx.getImageData", and then you ask for
the 00, the width and the height,
just like we did before. This might crash
my browser, but I'm going to try console
logging it. It's going to be millions of
pixels large, but let's see.
Whoa. Okay. So here we go. We've got this
sort of special kind of array here,
which is pixels.data is going to be a
special kind of array that's meant for
very, very large numbers. If you open up
one of those suckers...
Where did it go. Here. What if we did
this? "Console.log(pixels)",
and "debugger". Let's just stop it
altogether. There we go. I paused it.
Go back to our console. Look at some of
this image data. Open up the data.
There we go. We've got one, two, three,
four, five, six, 1.2 million items.
If you open up one of those and one of
those, and one of those,
here's the actual values. Now, what is
this? Well, "0" is going to be "R",
"1" is going to be "G", "B", "R", red,
green, blue, alpha. Red,
green, blue, alpha. So this array here is
simply just a huge array of numbers,
which is the first pixel is red, the first
pixel is green, the first pixel is blue,
I can't even remember, and then the first
pixel is alpha. Then,
it starts again. The second pixel is red,
green, blue, alpha. Red,
green, blue, alpha, and it just goes over
and over, and over. So for every one pixel
on this picture of me, you have four
entries in your array that describe the
red, the green, the blue, and the alpha.
So what we can then do is we take these
pixels, and this needs to be "let",
because we're going to reassign the pixels
array, not "const". It wouldn't let us do
that. We need to then take the pixels.
Say "pixels =" and let's do the red effect
first. I'll say "redEffect" and pass it
our pixels. Then, we go down here and
we'll make our filter function "redEffect"
, mix in our pixels, and then you loop
over every single pixel that you have.
Say "for (let i = 0); i < pixels.length".
If you're wondering why I'm not using .map
here, it's because this is a special kind
of array in JavaScript.
It doesn't have all of the regular array
method that you're used to working with.
You say "i = i + for" or "I += 4". That's
just going to increment it by four and not
by one. [inaudible 00:21:35] Then, we have
access to our red, green,
blue, and alpha, because "pixels[i]" is
going to be a red channel.
"I + 1" is going to be our green. "I +2"
is going to be our red,
green, blue, and then we actually don't
need to really mess with the alpha on this
redEffect on our own. So we say "pixels[i]
=", and then we can just start messing
with it and changing with the red, the
green, the blue, the one.
So I'm just going to paste some stuff in
here, and you can have some fun with it.
So what I've done here is I've just said
the first one plus zero,
I've just added a zero so I can see that
it's the first, second,
and third one that we have here, and I'm
just equaling it to itself plus 100,
the second one minus 50, and the third one
times 0.5. There's no rhyme or reason to
that. I just was messing with them. Some
of them are going to go over 255,
and some of them are going to go under,
and that's totally fine.
But what that will do is it'll give us a
bit of a cool effect.
What we do here is we return those pixels
once we've done messing with the actual
RGB values, and we go back up here where
"pixels = redEffect".
Then, we say "context.putImageData(pixels
0, 0)". That's going to,
if you take the pixels out... Maybe we
should put some comments here.
"Take the pixels out. Mess with them. Put
them back." So now, if we refresh this
sucker, I don't see a red effect happening
here. Why is that? "Let pixels =",
let's just debug this real quick. We've
got our pixels. We've got our pixels
coming back. We're putting it in. Any
errors in our console? Nope.
[inaudible 00:23:33], turning our pixels.
I'm not sure.
Oh, I figured out what it was. Our loop
is "pixels.data.length",
because "pixels" is not an array".
"Pixels.data" is an actual array.
So now if I save that, there we go. Now,
I've got this bit of a red effect going on
here, and we are seeing all of the
different colors being changed.
If you were to mess with this, like minus
100, you see you get a bit of a different
color effect. Or less 200, it will just
jack the red up really as high as we can
go. So that's the red effect. Next up,
what I want to do is what I like to call
the "RGB split". So I'll say "function
rgbSplit". That takes in our pixels,
and we're going to do exactly the same
thing that we did here.
So you can just copy and paste these
values into here. Except,
with our RGB split, what I'm going to do
instead of just changing each individual
one is I'm going to take the red and
change the one that is 150 pixels back to
be the current color. I'm going to take
the green, and take the pixel that is 150
pixels forward and set it to be the
current color. Then, I'll do the same
thing with the 150 pixels for the blue. So
I'm essentially just pulling apart the
different red, green, blues, and I'm
moving them to either side so that when
we're working it we're going to be able to
see the different ones that we're working
with. So I'm going to take that "rgbSplit"
function. I'm going to comment out this
pixels one. I'll use this one, "pixels =
rgbSplit(pixels)". Now,
when you refresh, you should see your red,
green, and your blue channels sort of
showing up where we have it. I think we
can go down here and maybe change this one
to 550 maybe. I don't know. I'm just m-...
There we go. You see the blue.
My face, which is blue, it's 550 pixels
off. Then, if I get to the edge of the
screen here, it starts to wrap around to
the other edge of the screen.
Because at a certain point, the pixels on
the very left-hand side,
it's going to wrap around. Of course, you
can play with this, make this 500.
Whoa. That's way more fun. I really like
that. Then, I also figured out that if you
go up right here and you take your CTX
Global Alpha to be 0.1,
what that's going to do is it's going to
right the actual one that we have.
But the ones that are underneath it are
still going to show through for 10 more
frames. The reason that that is, is
because we're just like putting a
transparency of 10% of the current image
on top, and we're just stacking and
stacking, and stacking. So as it goes, it
sort of like follows you around.
You can make that 0.8 and it would still
be ghosting, just a little bit less of an
actual ghosting effect. Woo. That's
really, really fun. Cool. Last one up,
we want to work with the green screen. So
we're going to go in here.
I have a function called "greenScreen".
That's going to take in our pixels.
Again, I'm just going to take this from
the answer here and explain it to you,
because there's a whole bunch of stuff
that's going on here. So I pasted it in
here. First of all, we've got this Levels
object here, and that's going to hold our
minimum and maximum green. Because the way
that green screen works is that you say,
"Give me all the colors in between this
RGB value, and take them out." Usually,
that's like you find a certain range of
special greens, and then you take those
ones out and they don't occur in the
people's clothing and what not.
So we have started with some blank levels.
Then, I've grabbed every single RGB input.
Actually, this conversion to array is no
longer needed. So that's all six of these
sliders here. Then, I've set the Red Min,
Red Max, Green Min, Green Max,
Blue Min, and Blue Max to be on that. So
if you were to console.log the levels,
and we were to go up here... Take off the
RGB split and the alpha.
Say "pixels = greenScreen(pixels)". Check
out our console here.
You see that we've got these objects
happening, which is going to give us the
Red Min, Red Max, etc. , etc. Okay? Good.
Then, we have a huge four-loop,
just like we've done before. We loop over
every single pixel, figure out what the
red, the green, the blue, and the alpha
are, and then we say, "The red and the
green, and the blue, and the red, and the
green, and the blue,
if it's anywhere in between those min and
max values," that's what this huge if
statement does, "we take it out." Why?
Because the fourth pixel is the alpha,
which is the transparency pixel, and if
you set that to zero, that's going to be
totally transparent. Rather than 255,
which would be totally there.
So if we give that a save now and you play
around with these sliders now,
you can just change your min and your max
red, green, and if you have a bit of a
green screen... Or I've done it before
where I've got a pink bristle board and
put it behind me, and I found that slice
of the rainbow where we want to pull that
specific pink or blue out. In this case,
I'm just pulling out random colors that
seem to match. It's kind of fun to work
with. So that is it. That was a big one.
I know that I went a little bit fast. But
this is one where I want you to go back
and just play with it. Start to make your
own filters. Now that you understand that
it's just a huge array of color values,
and especially if you understand how color
and math relate to each other, you can
start to make some really cool,
fun filters with them. I'd love to see any
of the filters that you do make.
Thanks a lot. Guess what?
I will see you tomorrow.
♪ [music] ♪